Finding Aid for Thomas A. Roach papers 1970-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas A. Roach Papers
1970-2002
Roach, Thomas A., 1929-
9743 AA 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan attorney, member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, 1975-1990, and Democratic Party official. Papers document his activities as regent and in local and state-wide Democratic Party affairs.
54 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by to the library by Thomas A. Roach (donor no. 7613) in 1991 and 1997. Additional materials came to the library in 2002.
The collection is open for research.
Thomas A. Roach is an attorney, an active participant within the Michigan Democratic party, and an elected public official. Born in Akron, Ohio on May 1, 1929, Roach graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1953. He commenced the practice of law in Detroit, Michigan, and eventually became partner in different Detroit and Ann Arbor law firms.
Beginning in the early 1970s, Roach began taking an active leadership role in local and statewide Democratic politics. Locally, from 1971 to 1975, he served as vice chairman of the 14th Congressional District Democratic Organization. Within the state party organization, he served in numerous positions, including chairman of the platform and resolution committee (1971-1974); party treasurer (1975-1987); and as convention parliamentarian and a member of various committees. In 1975, Roach ran successfully for public office as a regent of the University of Michigan and served in this position until 1990.
The papers of Thomas Roach measure fifty-four linear feet and date from 1970 to 2002. These records document the public career of Roach as a Regent of the University of Michigan and a longtime active participant in the Michigan Democratic Party. The papers are divided into three series: Democratic Party Files, Board of Regents Files and Post-Regental Activities.
Subjects:
Roach, Thomas A., 1929-; Democratic Party (Mich.); Disinvestment--South Africa.; Investments, American--South Africa.; South Africa--Foreign economic relations--United States.; United States--Foreign economic relations--South Africa.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.
- Democratic Party files
  The five linear feet of Democratic Party Files are arranged alphabetically by topic and reflect Roach's activities within this organization. The substantial "Party Leadership" files contain meeting agendas, memoranda, and correspondence of the party officers. The "Budgets" files contains financial records of the party, stemming from Roach's tenure as treasurer. The "Reapportionment" files relates to congressional redistricting in Michigan following the 1980 census. Other policy issues covered in these papers include "No Fault Legislation," "the "Bingo Tax Issue," and "Election Data Services." Many of the other files in this series concern Roach's participation in different Democratic Party committees, groups, and events. Of these, the "Rules Committee of the Democratic National Convention" files are the most significant and provide information both on the committee and the specific role Roach played in it.
  - Topical files
    - Bingo Tax Issue, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Budgets, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1989; 12 folders (Box 1)
    - DemList Agreement (Database of Democrats), 1986 (Box 1)
    - Democratic Club of Grosse Point Park, Michigan, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - Democratic Sing-A-Long (Box 1)
    - Economic Advisory Council, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Election Data Services, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Governor's Leadership Workshop, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Higher Education Task Force, 1980-1983; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Jackson (Henry M.) for President, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Leadership Retreat, Spring 1981 (Box 1)
    - Leadership Training Manuals, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - New Opportunity Democrats, 1985 (Box 1)
    - "No Fault" Legislation, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Party Leadership, 1975-1979; 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Party Leadership, 1980-1987; 14 folders (Box 2)
    - Personnel Policy, circa 1974 (Box 2)
    - Proportional Voting Subcommittee, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Reapportionment, 1981-1982
      - Agreement (Box 2)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Drafts and Notes (Box 2)
      - Final Plans (Senate and House of Representatives) (Box 2)
      - Legal Documents and Contracts (Box 2)
    - Rules Committee of the Democratic National Convention, 1980
      - Agenda, July 8-9, 1980 (Box 2)
      - General Files, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - State and district convention files (mainly relating to work with party platform and resolution committee)
    - 1971 (Box 52)
    - 1972 (Box 52)
    - 1973 (Box 52)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 52)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 53)
  - Campaign for U-M Board of Regents
    - 1970 (Box 53)
    - 1972 (Box 53)
    - 1974 (Box 54)
    - 1982
      - Biographical Information (Box 54)
      - Campaign Strategies (Box 54)
      - Candidate Questionnaires (Box 54)
      - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 54)
      - Congratulatory Letters (Box 54)
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 54)
      - Democratic Party (Box 54)
      - Events (Box 54)
      - Press Kit (Box 54)
      - Press Releases (Box 54)
      - Speech Materials (Box 54)
- Board of Regents Files
  - Correspondence
    Board of Regents Files primarily document Roach's activity in his capacity as Regent of the University of Michigan and are divided into five subseries: Correspondence, Roach for Regent, Speeches, Topical Files, and Regents' Agendas and Exhibits.
    The Correspondence subseries contains both official and informal communications to and from Roach. Many letters serve as petitions to Regent Roach and therefore reflect the concerns and praises of individual citizens and groups about the functioning of the university. Much correspondence between Roach and university officials, including other regents, the university president, and other executive officers comprise a large amount of this subseries. Also included are some memoranda addressed collectively to the Board of Regents from the executive officers of the university, especially the Office of the President, but researchers should also consult the record groups for those university offices for more extensive coverage of the issues discussed in these communications.
    - 1975-1989, 34 folders (Box 3)
    - 1989-1990, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Roach for Regent
    The Roach for Regent subseries contains campaign materials from Roach's unsuccessful bid for election in 1972 and his successful re-election in 1982. The bulk of these materials document the 1982 campaign. There is, unfortunately, little information on Roach's first successful campaign in 1975. The "Biographical Information" file in this subseries includes a vitae for Roach along with other materials illuminating his life, and "Candidate Questionnaires" from both 1972 and 1982 provide information on his political views.
    - (Candidate Questionnaire), 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1982
      - Biographical Information (Box 4)
      - Campaign Strategies (Box 4)
      - Candidate Questionnaires (Box 4)
      - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Congratulatory Letters (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Democratic Party (Box 4)
      - Events (Box 4)
      - Press Kit (Box 4)
      - Press Releases (Box 4)
      - Speech Materials (Box 4)
  - Speech File
    The Speech subseries contains notes for speeches Roach made while a Regent along with information on the venue or audience. The file is arranged alphabetically by place and event, and titles and dates have been provided where discernible. The full text of the speech "Allocation of Scarce Medical Resources" is included in the "Conference on Ethics, Humanism, and Medicine" file.
    - Association of College Unions, October 19, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Conference on Ethics, Humanism, and Medicine, November 11, 1978. ("Allocation of Scarce Medical Resources") (Box 4)
    - Emeritus Club, August 11, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Farm and Industrial Equipment Institute, May 22, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Hospital Volunteers, April 20, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Leadership Ann Arbor, February 18, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Oakland University (University of Michigan South Africa Investment Policy), December 6, 1978 (Box 4)
    - ROTC, April 8, 1986 (Box 4)
    - School Of Music Honors Assembly ("Excellence in the 80s at Michigan"), April 7, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Senior Class Leadership, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Sesquicentennial Speech, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Shapiro Roast, circa 1983 (Box 4)
    - Torch Club of Detroit ("A Regent Looks at Higher Education"), January 20, 1983 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan-Dearborn Library Dedication, April 11, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Topical File
    Measuring more than three linear feet and arranged alphabetically, the Topical subseries documents regental activity in which Roach was particularly active. The records in this subseries are diverse and include correspondence, memoranda, reports, meeting agendas, and other miscellanea relating to a specific topic. Included are files relating to the "Campaign for Michigan"and the University of Michigan's South Africa Investment Policy. The "Campaign for Michigan" files include records from a major university fund-raising campaign for which Roach served as National Coordinator for Special Gifts. Roach also played a major role in the debates of the late 1970s and early 1980s over the appropriateness the university's investments in South Africa. The records in the "South Africa Investment Policy" files provide excellent documentation of the issues and events surrounding this debate and of Roach's participation in them. Of special interest is the "Indicia of Excellence" file consisting of reports from the different schools, colleges, and departments within the university on what they believed to be the finest aspects of their units. Finally, the records in the "Commission on the Future of Higher Education" files offer excellent documentation of Roach's participation on this important state board.
    - Affirmative Action, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Alumni Association Speaking Tour (Texas), 1984 (Box 4)
    - Alumni Association Speaking Tour (West Coast), 1985 (Box 4)
    - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), 1977-1978; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Court Club, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Annual Giving, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Barbour-Waterman Gymnasium, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - Big Ten Governing Board, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Camp Filbert Roth, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Campaign for Michigan (Box 5)
      - Campaign Plan, 1983 (Box 5)
      - City Files, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1986-1988 (Box 5)
      - Development Study, circa 1979 (Box 5)
      - Organization Plan, 1985 (Box 5)
      - National Leadership Meeting, October 29, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Post-campaign Materials, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - Regents Briefing, May 1983 (Box 5)
      - Reports, 1985-1988 (Box 5)
      - Special Gifts Phase, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Classified Research, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Code of Non-Academic Conduct, 1984-1986 (Box 5)
    - College of Engineering, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Commission on the Future of Higher Education
      - Congressional Testimony, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    - Development Council, 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Dunn, Gerald and Robert Nederlander Retirement, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Food Service Consolidation, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Fort Meigs Treaty, 1975 (Box 5)
      (Native American Land Claim)
    - Geography Department, 1981 (Box 5)
      (Discontinuance of)
    - Graduate Employees Organization (GEO), 1976-1982; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - High Technology Research Park, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Historic District Designation, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Housing, 1975-1979 (Box 6)
    - "Indicia of Excellence,", 1984 (Box 6)
    - Institute for Labor and Industrial Relations, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Meeting Notes, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Association of Governing Boards, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
    - Michigan House, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Student Assembly, 1985-1989; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Michigan Union, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
    - Non-recurring Fund Allocation, 1981-1983 (Box 6)
    - Non-Resident Students, 1987 (Box 6)
    - Open Meetings Act, 1976-1978 (Box 6)
    - Open Meetings Act, 1982-1984 (Box 6)
    - Partners in Leadership, 1990 (Box 6)
    - "Passing Up," (student football game ritual) (Box 6)
    - Physical Therapy Program Review, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Planning Advisory Board, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Population Planning, 1976-1978; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - "Profiles and Election/Selection Procedures," (of Board of Regents), 1983 (Box 6)
    - Public Interest Research Group In Michigan (PIRGIM), 1975-77, 1981; 1984-1986; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Quadrium Complex, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Radulovic, Douglas, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Real Estate Extension Program, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Regents' By-Laws, 1985 (Box 7)
    - Regents' Retreats, 1976; 1977; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Replacement Hospital Program
      - Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 7)
      - Meeting Transcript, June 19, 1980 (Box 7)
      - Meeting Transcript, April 17, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Residency Requirements, 1975-1977 (Box 7)
    - Retirement Parties, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Rhodes, Frank, 1977 (Box 7)
    - School of Natural Resources Review, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Senior Men's Club, Grosse Pointe, Michigan, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Sexual Orientation, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
    - Solomon Amendment, 1983 (Box 7)
    - South Africa Investment Policy
      - Background Materials, 1978 (Box 7)
      - Clippings, 1977-1982; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Compliance Reports, 1978 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1977-1983; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Divestment Debate Remarks, April 14, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Forum, January 30, 1978 (Box 7)
      - Information Packet, 1978-1983 (Box 7)
      - Resolutions, 1978-1983 (Box 7)
      - Teach-In, November, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Student Legal Services, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Students With Disabilities, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Tisch Amendment, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Trustee Leadership in Michigan Conference, October 30-31, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Tuition Increases, 1988 (Box 7)
      (Communication with Governor Blanchard)
    - University Hospital, 1977 (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan-Dearborn Campus, 1977-1987; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan Dearborn Campus Student Government, 1983 (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan Extension Services, 1976 (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan-Flint Campus, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Regents Agendas and Exhibits
    The final subseries - Regents' Agendas and Exhibits - forms the bulk of the collection and includes materials distributed to each regent at their monthly meetings. These files are of interest because of Roach's occasional marginal notes. This subseries covers the period of 1974 to 1990 and should be consulted in conjunction with the library's other holdings of Regents' Agendas and Exhibits (filed in the catalog as University of Michigan. Board of Regents).
    - November 1974-March 1975 (Box 8)
    - April 1975-July 1975 (Box 9)
    - September 1975-January 1976 (Box 10)
    - February 1976-August 1976 (Box 11)
    - September 1976-December 1976 (Box 12)
    - January 1977-June 1977 (Box 13)
    - July 1977-October 1977 (Box 14)
    - November 1977-April 1978 (Box 15)
    - May 1978-Spetember (Box 16)
    - October 1978-December 1978 (Box 17)
    - January 1979-April 1979 (Box 18)
    - May 1979-July 1979 (Box 19)
    - September 1979-January 1980 (Box 20)
    - February 1980-June 1980 (Box 21)
    - July 1980-November 1980 (Box 22)
    - December 1980-April 1981 (Box 23)
    - May 1981-September 1981 (Box 24)
    - October 1981-January 1982 (Box 25)
    - February 1982-May 1982 (Box 26)
    - June 1982-October 1982 (Box 27)
    - November 1982-April 1983 (Box 28)
    - May 1983-July 1983 (Box 29)
    - September 1983-November 1983 (Box 30)
    - December 1983-April 1984 (Box 31)
    - May 1984-July 1984 (Box 32)
    - September 1984-December 1984 (Box 33)
    - January 1985-May 1985 (Box 34)
    - June 1985-September 1985 (Box 35)
    - October 1985-February 1986 (Box 36)
    - March 1986-May 1986 (Box 37)
    - June 1986-September 1986 (Box 38)
    - October 1986-January 1987 (Box 39)
    - February 1987-May 1987 (Box 40)
    - June 1987 (Box 41)
    - July 1987-November 1987 (Box 42)
    - December 1987-March 1988 (Box 43)
    - April 1988-July 1988 (Box 44)
    - September 1988-December 1988 (Box 45)
    - January 1989-May 1989 (Box 46)
    - June 1989-September 1989 (Box 47)
    - October 1989-March 1990 (Box 48)
    - April 1990-July 1990 (Box 49)
    - September 1990-December 1990 (Box 50)
- Post-Regental Activities
  - Alumni Association (Box 51)
  - Emeritus Club (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 51)
Related material:
Board of Regents (University of Michigan) records, 1817-[ongoing].